<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
   Copyright (C) The Internet Society (2002).  All Rights Reserved.

   This document and translations of it may be copied and furnished to
   others, and derivative works that comment on or otherwise explain it
   or assist in its implementation may be prepared, copied, published
   and distributed, in whole or in part, without restriction of any
   kind, provided that the above copyright notice and this paragraph are
   included on all such copies and derivative works.  However, this
   document itself may not be modified in any way, such as by removing
   the copyright notice or references to the Internet Society or other
   Internet organizations, except as needed for the purpose of
   developing Internet standards in which case the procedures for
   copyrights defined in the Internet Standards process must be
   followed, or as required to translate it into languages other than
   English.

   The limited permissions granted above are perpetual and will not be
   revoked by the Internet Society or its successors or assigns.

   This document and the information contained herein is provided on an
   "AS IS" basis and THE INTERNET SOCIETY AND THE INTERNET ENGINEERING
   TASK FORCE DISCLAIMS ALL WARRANTIES, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING
   BUT NOT LIMITED TO ANY WARRANTY THAT THE USE OF THE INFORMATION
   HEREIN WILL NOT INFRINGE ANY RIGHTS OR ANY IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF
   MERCHANTABILITY OR FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.
-->
<glossary>
  <glossentry id="gloss-adv">
    <glossterm>Advertisement</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>JXTA's language-neutral metadata structures that describe peer
      resources such as peers, peer groups, pipes, and services. Advertisements
      are represented as XML documents.</para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id="gloss-binding">
    <glossterm>Binding</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>An implementation of the JXTA protocols for a particular 
      environment (e.g., the Java J2SE platform binding).</para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id="gloss-codat">
    <glossterm>Codat</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>The combination of a content (commonly a document or file) and a
      JXTA ID.</para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id="gloss-credential">
    <glossterm>Credential</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>A token used to uniquely identify the sender of a message; can be 
      used to provide message authorization.</para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id="gloss-jxta">
    <glossterm>JXTA</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>JXTA is not an acronym, and in particular the 
      <quote>J</quote>does not refer to Java. JXTA is a made up word coined
      by the project's original sponsor, Bill Joy. JXTA is derived from the
      word Juxtapose, as in side by side. It is a recognition that
      peer-to-peer is juxtaposed to client server or Web based computing --
      what is considered today's traditional computing model.</para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            <emphasis role="bold">jux ta pose</emphasis>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <simpara>
            <emphasis>tr. v.</emphasis>To place side by side, especially for
            comparison or contrast.</simpara>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id="gloss-jcs">
    <glossterm>JXTA Core Specification</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>The JXTA Core Specification consists of the required components
      and behaviours which are present in all conforming JXTA
      implementations. This includes the Endpoint Routing Protocol 
      (<acronym>ERP</acronym>) and the Peer Resolver Protocol 
      (<acronym>PRP</acronym>).</para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id="gloss-idformat">
    <glossterm>JXTA ID Format</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>A JXTA ID Format is a scheme for representing it IDs of JXTA
      entities. Each ID Format is identified by as sub-namespace of the URN
      namespace "jxta".</para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id="gloss-idtype">
    <glossterm>JXTA ID Type</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>A JXTA ID Type is describes the characteristics of JXTA IDs which
      refer to a particular sort of JXTA entity. Currently this includes peer
      groups, peers, codats, pipes, module classes, module specifications and
      module impelmentations, but may be extended to refer to other types of
      entities in the future or in specific implementations.</para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id="gloss-jss">
    <glossterm>JXTA Standard Services</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>The JXTA Standard Services are optional JXTA components and
      behaviours. Implementations are not required to provide these services,
      but are strongly <phrase role="rfc2119">recommended</phrase> to do so.
      This includes Peer Discovery Protocol (<acronym>PDP</acronym>),
      Peer Information Protocol (<acronym>PIP</acronym>),
      Pipe Binding Protocol (<acronym>PBP</acronym>) and
      Rendezvous Protocol (<acronym>RVP</acronym>).</para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id="gloss-message">
    <glossterm>Message</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>The basic unit of data exchange between JXTA peers; each message 
      contains an ordered sequence of named sub-sections, called message 
      elements, which can hold any form of data.</para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="gloss-messageTransport">
    <glossterm>Message Transport</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>A Message Transport is responsible for sending and/or receiving JXTA
      messages via an external network. A Message Transport may use whatever
      wire protocol it wishes in order to transmit messages between peers. 
      Message Transports <phrase role="rfc2119">must</phrase> pass the messages 
      between peers unaltered.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id="gloss-module">
    <glossterm>Module</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>An abstraction used to represent any piece of "code" used to 
      implement a behavior in the JXTA world. Network services are the mode 
      common example of behavior that can be instantiated on a peer.</para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id="gloss-moduleclass">
    <glossterm>Module Class</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>Represents an expected behavior and an expected binding to support 
      the module; is used primarily to advertise the existence of a behavior.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id="gloss-moduleimpl">
    <glossterm>Module Implementation</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>The implementation of a given module specification; there may be 
      multiple module implementations for a given module specification.</para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id="gloss-modulespec">
    <glossterm>Module Specification</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>Describes a specification of a given module class; it is one 
      approach to providing the functionality that a module class implies. There
      can be multiple module specifications for a given module class. The module
      specification is primarily used to access a module.</para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  <glossentry id="gloss-p2p">
    

  <glossentry id="gloss-netgroup">
    <glossterm>network Peer Group</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>The base peer group for applications and services within the JXTA 
      network. Most applications and services will instantiate their own peer 
      groups using the Network Peer Group as a base.</para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossterm>Peer-to-Peer</glossterm>
    <acronym>P2P</acronym>
    <glossdef>
      <para>A decentralized networking paradigm in which distributed nodes,
      or peers, communicate and work collaboratively to provide services.</para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry id="gloss-peer">
    <glossterm>Peer</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>A peer is any uniquely identifiable networked device which is 
      capable of interacting with other network devices using standardized
      protocols.</para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="gloss-peergroup">
    <glossterm>Peer Group</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>A collection of peers that have a common set of interests and have 
      agreed upon a common set of services.</para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="gloss-prp">
    <glossterm>Peer Resolver Protocol</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>The Peer Resolver Protocol provides a generic query/response 
      interface applications and services can use for building resolution 
      services. </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="gloss-rdv">
    <glossterm>Rendezvous Peer</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>A peer which assumes additional responsibilities for the propagation
      of messages within a peer group.</para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="gloss-resolverservice">
    <glossterm>Resolver Service</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>Resolver Services are responsible for the routing and processing
      queries and responses within peer groups. Resolver Services use the Peer
      Resolver Protocol (<acronym>PRP</acronym>) for transmission of
      queries between peers.</para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="gloss-xml">
    <glossterm><acronym>XML</acronym></glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>(From <citetitle pubwork="article">Extensible Markup Language (XML) 1.0</citetitle>
      <xref linkend="bib-XML10"/> ) :
      Extensible Markup Language, abbreviated <acronym>XML</acronym>, describes
      a class of data objects called <acronym>XML</acronym> documents and 
      partially describes the behavior ofcomputer programs which process them.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry id="gloss-worldgroup">
    <glossterm>World Peer Group</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>The most fundamental peer group within the JXTA network. This core 
      peer group is generally responsible only for management of physical 
      network connections, physical network (generally broadcast) discovery and 
      physical network topology management. Applications generally do not 
      interact with this group. May only include limited endpoint, resolver, 
      discovery and rendezvous services.</para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glossary>
