<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--
   Copyright (C) The Internet Society (2002).  All Rights Reserved.

   This document and translations of it may be copied and furnished to
   others, and derivative works that comment on or otherwise explain it
   or assist in its implementation may be prepared, copied, published
   and distributed, in whole or in part, without restriction of any
   kind, provided that the above copyright notice and this paragraph are
   included on all such copies and derivative works.  However, this
   document itself may not be modified in any way, such as by removing
   the copyright notice or references to the Internet Society or other
   Internet organizations, except as needed for the purpose of
   developing Internet standards in which case the procedures for
   copyrights defined in the Internet Standards process must be
   followed, or as required to translate it into languages other than
   English.

   The limited permissions granted above are perpetual and will not be
   revoked by the Internet Society or its successors or assigns.

   This document and the information contained herein is provided on an
   "AS IS" basis and THE INTERNET SOCIETY AND THE INTERNET ENGINEERING
   TASK FORCE DISCLAIMS ALL WARRANTIES, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING
   BUT NOT LIMITED TO ANY WARRANTY THAT THE USE OF THE INFORMATION
   HEREIN WILL NOT INFRINGE ANY RIGHTS OR ANY IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF
   MERCHANTABILITY OR FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.
-->

<abstract>
<para>
The JXTA protocols defines a suite of six XML-based protocols that standardize 
the manner in which peers self-organize into peergroups, publish and discover 
peer resources, communicate, and monitor each other. The Endpoint Routing 
Protocol (ERP) is the protocol by which a peer can discover a route (sequence 
of hops) to send a message to another peer potentially traversing firewalls and 
NATs. The Rendezvous Protocol (RVP) is used for propagating a message within a 
peergroup. The Peer Resolver Protocol (PRP) is the protocol used to send a 
generic query to one or more peers, and receive a response (or multiple 
responses) to the query. The Peer Discovery Protocol (PDP) is used to publish 
and discover resource advertisements. The Peer Information Protocol (PIP) is 
the protocol by a which a peer may obtain status information about another 
peers. The Pipe Binding Protocol (PBP) is the protocol by which a peer can 
establish a virtual communication channel or pipe between one or more peers.
The JXTA protocols permit the establishment a virtual network overlay on top of 
physical networks allowing peers to directly interact and organize 
independently of their network location and connectivity. The JXTA protocols 
have been designed to be easily implemented on unidirectional links and
asymmetric transports.
</para>
</abstract>

