<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
   Copyright (C) The Internet Society (2002).  All Rights Reserved.

   This document and translations of it may be copied and furnished to
   others, and derivative works that comment on or otherwise explain it
   or assist in its implementation may be prepared, copied, published
   and distributed, in whole or in part, without restriction of any
   kind, provided that the above copyright notice and this paragraph are
   included on all such copies and derivative works.  However, this
   document itself may not be modified in any way, such as by removing
   the copyright notice or references to the Internet Society or other
   Internet organizations, except as needed for the purpose of
   developing Internet standards in which case the procedures for
   copyrights defined in the Internet Standards process must be
   followed, or as required to translate it into languages other than
   English.

   The limited permissions granted above are perpetual and will not be
   revoked by the Internet Society or its successors or assigns.

   This document and the information contained herein is provided on an
   "AS IS" basis and THE INTERNET SOCIETY AND THE INTERNET ENGINEERING
   TASK FORCE DISCLAIMS ALL WARRANTIES, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING
   BUT NOT LIMITED TO ANY WARRANTY THAT THE USE OF THE INFORMATION
   HEREIN WILL NOT INFRINGE ANY RIGHTS OR ANY IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF
   MERCHANTABILITY OR FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.
-->
<revhistory>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>1.2</revnumber>
    <date>June 22, 2001</date>
    <authorinitials>goober@jxta.org,</authorinitials>
    <revremark>preliminary DocBook format</revremark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>1.2.2</revnumber>
    <date>September 22, 2001</date>
    <authorinitials>goober@jxta.org</authorinitials>
    <revremark>first release based on DocBook format (no intended changes
    from 1.2 revision)</revremark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>1.2.3</revnumber>
    <date>November 20, 2001</date>
    <authorinitials>bondolo@jxta.org</authorinitials>
    <revremark>Updates to the IDs chapter to document new IDs design.
    Information on components provided as part of reference implementations
    is also being moved to the reference implementation section (this may
    eventually be a separate document).</revremark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>1.2.4</revnumber>
    <date>November 20, 2001</date>
    <revremark>Updates to Protocol chapter, discovery behavior and minor
    changes to the Resolver section.</revremark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>1.2.5</revnumber>
    <date>November 21, 2001</date>
    <authorinitials>bondolo@jxta.org</authorinitials>
    <revremark>Updates to Advertisements chapter, added sections for
    ModuleClassAdvertisement, ModuleSpecAdvertisement,
    ModuleImplAdvertisement. Updated sections for PeerAdvertisement and
    PeerGroupAdvertisement.</revremark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>1.2.6</revnumber>
    <date>November 28, 2001</date>
    <authorinitials>bondolo@jxta.org</authorinitials>
    <revremark>Updates to Advertisements chapter, added sections for
    PeerInfoAdvertisement. also includes typo corrections in various
    sections</revremark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>1.2.7</revnumber>
    <date>November 29, 2001</date>
    <authorinitials>bondolo@jxta.org</authorinitials>
    <revremark>Updates to the Protocol Section, and more description on
    PeerInfoAdvertisement traffic field</revremark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>1.2.8</revnumber>
    <date>December, 2001</date>
    <authorinitials>bondolo@jxta.org</authorinitials>
    <revremark>Integrated docbookized version of Eric's sections about
    enpoint service and router. Made some cosmetic fixes per last
    review.</revremark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>1.2.9</revnumber>
    <date>December 4, 2001</date>
    <authorinitials>bondolo@jxta.org</authorinitials>
    <revremark>Updates to protocols chapter to use schemas to describe
    message structure more formally. Remove Peer Membership Protocol. Remove
    Content Advertisement (may be readded in documentation of CMS, but not
    part of or used by core protocols) Minor cosmetic improvements to
    copyright and ids chapter.</revremark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>1.2.10</revnumber>
    <date>December 7, 2001</date>
    <authorinitials>bondolo@jxta.org</authorinitials>
    <revremark>Updates to protocols chapter to use mores schemas to describe
    message structure more formally. Examples for each as well.</revremark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>1.2.11</revnumber>
    <date>December 7, 2001</date>
    <authorinitials>bondolo@jxta.org</authorinitials>
    <revremark>More updates to the protocols chapter. Converting raw program
    listings to figures and examples, addition of live cross references.
    Preparing for glossary and bibliography.</revremark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>1.2.12</revnumber>
    <date>December 9, 2001</date>
    <authorinitials>bondolo@jxta.org</authorinitials>
    <revremark>More updates to the protocols chapter. PeerInfoProtocol and
    Pipe Binding Protocol now have schemas. Converting raw program listings
    to figures and examples, addition of live cross references. Preparing for
    glossary and bibliography. Cosmetic changes to Messages
    chapter</revremark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>1.2.13</revnumber>
    <date>December 17, 2001</date>
    <authorinitials>bondolo@jxta.org</authorinitials>
    <revremark>Peer Info Protocol was redone because the previous schema
    though XML-like, was not representable with XML. (Endpoint Addresses as
    tag names were the culprit). PIP now looks more like the Peer Discovery
    Protocol with separate schemas for query and response. Document has been
    restructured into three major sections; Core Specification, Standard
    Services, and Reference Implementations. This restructuring makes
    understanding the JXTA Protocols more straight-forward because
    requirements and behaviours are now divided between functionality
    required by all JXTA peers, functionality needed to interoperate with the
    optional JXTA Protocols, and functionality required to interoperate with
    specific JXTA implementations.</revremark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>1.3</revnumber>
    <date>January 3, 2002</date>
    <revremark>Wrote introductions for each of the new document sections.
    Introduced a glossary and bibliography. More restructuring of the source
    docbook files. Changes to prepare for a printable form
    document.</revremark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>1.3.1</revnumber>
    <date>January 9, 2002</date>
    <authorinitials>bondolo@jxta.org</authorinitials>
    <revremark>Spelling and grammar corrections. More reorganization of
    material into core, standard services and reference implementation parts.
    Updating stylesheets and docbook usage based on techniques seen in other
    docbook projects.</revremark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>1.3.2</revnumber>
    <date>January 9, 2002</date>
    <authorinitials>bondolo@jxta.org</authorinitials>
    <revremark>More moving content around into core and standard services.
    More chapters reorganized. New text in advertisments chapter. More
    bibliographic information.</revremark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>1.3.3</revnumber>
    <date>January 14, 2002</date>
    <authorinitials>bondolo@jxta.org</authorinitials>
    <revremark>Redid the schemas for the advertisement chapter. Moved all of
    the protocol advertisements and schemas to the appropriate protocols
    chapters. Use of &lt;literal&gt; has now been replaced with
    &lt;phrase&gt; and a role attribute of 
    <emphasis>rfc2119</emphasis>. Improved field descriptions for some of the
    core advertisements.</revremark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>1.3.4</revnumber>
    <date>February 13, 2002</date>
    <authorinitials>bondolo@jxta.org</authorinitials>
    <revremark>Lots of minor revisions based on review cycle. Thanks to all
    of the reviewers who took time to review and respond!</revremark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>1.3.5</revnumber>
    <date>April 19, 2002</date>
    <authorinitials>bondolo@jxta.org</authorinitials>
    <revremark>Redid some of the schema descriptions in a new and clearer
    style, more will be converted of over time. Redid schemas and examples
    for Pipe Binding Protocol section. A few changes to FO generation which
    generates 
    <emphasis>much</emphasis>better PDF output. Corrected a few specific
    issues pointed out by Brendon Wilson.</revremark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>1.3.6</revnumber>
    <date>June 10, 2002</date>
    <authorinitials>bondolo@jxta.org</authorinitials>
    <revremark>More complete documentation of the Pipe Binding Protocol based
    upon review of the J2SE and C implementations. Partial re-write of the
    Messages chapter to flesh out some of the details. Remove text not
    specific to the protocol (mostly dealing with namespace ":"
    name).</revremark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>1.3.7</revnumber>
    <date>June 11, 2002</date>
    <authorinitials>bondolo@jxta.org</authorinitials>
    <revremark>Minor corrections following review. Now has an "Abstract"
    section.</revremark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>1.3.8</revnumber>
    <date>June 18, 2002</date>
    <authorinitials>bondolo@jxta.org</authorinitials>
    <revremark>Lots of corrections following a detailed review by Jeff
    Altman, with many more corrections to come! A bit of reorganisation of
    the messages chapter into two pieces. Some cleanups for TOC generation in
    the HTML version. Still working on SVG figures. Next release will be 1.4
    upon completion of all the feedback cleanups.</revremark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>1.4</revnumber>
    <date>June 19, 2002</date>
    <authorinitials>bondolo@jxta.org</authorinitials>
    <revremark>The Docbook source now validates against the Docbook 4.2 DTD.
    This seemingly minor issue fixed a number of problems with the HTML, PDF
    and rfc 2629 renderings and cross-referencing. Implemented all of the
    feedback from the most recent review cycle. Fixed a number of the
    figures.</revremark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>1.4.1</revnumber>
    <date>June 21, 2002</date>
    <authorinitials>bondolo@jxta.org</authorinitials>
    <revremark>More revisions following careful review. This version is being
    released to coincide with the submission of the JXTA Specification as an
    Internet-Draft to IETF.</revremark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>1.4.2</revnumber>
    <date>October 10, 2002</date>
    <authorinitials>bondolo@jxta.org</authorinitials>
    <revremark>Updates to Standard Transports sections. Updates to the
    Endpoint Routing Protocol and Endpoint Router Transport. Adds new
    optional SRDI message for Endpoint Resolver Protocol. Minor textual
    improvements and clarifications elsewhere. New examples and
    figures.</revremark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>2.0</revnumber>
    <date>February 27, 2003</date>
    <authorinitials>bondolo@jxta.org</authorinitials>
    <revremark>Updates to Standard Transports sections. Clarifications in the
    IDs section. Updates to the Pipe Resolver protocol. Minor textual
    improvements and clarifications elsewhere. Added a section on "Users and
    Peers". Added a number of glossary terms. More contributions to the
    glossary are welcome. Updated version to "2.0". Rewrote or revised much
    of the Overview chapter.</revremark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>2.1.1</revnumber>
    <date>October 15, 2003</date>
    <authorinitials>bondolo@jxta.org</authorinitials>
    <revremark>Additional updates to the Introduction and Overview chapters. 
    Many additions to the glossary section. Minor schema corrections.
    </revremark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>2.2.1</revnumber>
    <date>April 10th, 2004</date>
    <authorinitials>bondolo@jxta.org</authorinitials>
    <revremark>Additional updates to glossary and bibliography. Added updates to
    pipes regarding propagate pipes.
    </revremark>
  </revision>
    <revision>
    <revnumber>2.3</revnumber>
    <date>June 30th, 2004</date>
    <authorinitials>bondolo@jxta.org</authorinitials>
    <revremark>Additional information about the Rendezvous, Resolver and Pipe
    Services.
    </revremark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>2.3.5</revnumber>
    <date>September 20th, 2005</date>
    <authorinitials>mathieu@jxta.org</authorinitials>
    <revremark>Homogeneous spec for Resolver queries and responses.
    </revremark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>2.5</revnumber>
    <date>June 23rd, 2006</date>
    <authorinitials>bondolo@jxta.org</authorinitials>
    <revremark>Clarifications to the HTTP Message Transport.
    </revremark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>2.5.1</revnumber>
    <date>August 23rd, 2006</date>
    <authorinitials>bondolo@jxta.org</authorinitials>
    <revremark>Corrections and clarifications to Route Advertisement 
    and Pipe Resolver Message.</revremark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>2.5.2</revnumber>
    <date>January 9th, 2007</date>
    <authorinitials>bondolo@jxta.org</authorinitials>
    <revremark>Corrections and clarifications from several sharp eyed readers.
    Now includes complete specification of Binary Message Format version 2 and
    specification of the endpoint SrcAddess and DstAddress message elements.
    </revremark>
  </revision>
  <revision>
    <revnumber>2.5.3</revnumber>
    <date>October 16th, 2007</date>
    <authorinitials>bondolo@jxta.org</authorinitials>
    <revremark>Additional glossary entries and other minor corrections.
    </revremark>
  </revision>
</revhistory>
